Guide to the Carl L. Withers Manuscript Collection RISM.MC.1
New York University Archives
- Series VI. Unpublished Manuscripts
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 300 - 399 [pp. 385 blank, 423 missing], Sep 1948 - Oct 1948 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 401 - 499, Sep 1948 - Oct 1948 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 500 - 599, May 1948 - Dec 1948 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 600 - 699[pp. 666 and 687 missing], Dec 1949 - Jan 1949 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 700 - 799 [p. 761 missing], Jan 1949 - Apr 1949 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 800 - 899, Jan 1949 - Apr 1949 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 900 - 999 [pp. 955 - 984 misnumbered], Apr 1949 - May 1949 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 1000 - 1072, May 1949 - Jun 1949 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 1073 - 1175[pp. 1111, 1126-1129 missing], Jun 1949 - Aug 1949 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 1176-1230, Aug 1949 - Sep 1949 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 1231 - 1299, Sep 1949 - Oct 1949 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 1300 - 1399, Oct 1949 - Nov 1949 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 1400 - 1480, Nov 1949 - Dec 1949 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - The Manolo Manuscript pp. 1481 - 1515, Jan 1950 - Dec 1950, Mar 1951 - Aug 1951 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Series VII. Studies in American Youth Culture
  0.5 linear feet, arranged chronologically. This series documents Carl Withers' work for the Children's Bureau of the U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare. The papers include an outlined study for a pilot study of American youth culture and several articles and journals that focus on related topics.
  - A Sociopsychological Study of Adolescent Conformity and Deviation, published by the U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare, and notes, Oct 1958 - Oct 1959 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Outlines for planned study of American youth culture, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - The American Journal of Sociology, Jul 1960 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Explorations in Creative Thinking in the Early School Years: XI. Changing Reactions of Girls in Grades Four Through Six to Tasks Requiring Creative Scientific Thinking, by E. Paul Torrance, Aug 1960 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Explorations in Creative Thinking in the Early School Years: XII. Social Stress in Homogeneous and Heterogeneous Groups, by E. Paul Torrance, Aug 1960 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Factors Affecting Creative Thinking in Children, draft symposium paper prepared by E. Paul Torrance, Sep 1960 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - The Sexual Dilemma of the Caribbean Adolescent, J. Herbert Fill, M.D., Apr 1961 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Why Students of the Natural Sciences Abandon Careers in Science, Carl Nordstrom and Edgar Z. Friedenberg; Why Students Leave Science; Commentary Report by Edgar Z. Friedenberg, Jun 1961, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - "Youth, The Cool Generation," The Saturday Evening Post, Dec 1961 (Box 18, Folder 9)
- Series VIII. Personal Writings
  This series contains undated, handwritten notes from a lecture given by Withers at Yale University, possibly after his return from Cuba and a stenographic notebook of personal observations written during his last years. Also included are materials by or about Withers.
  - Yale lecture notes on Cuba; hand-drawn map, 1950 - 1960 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Journal entries, Jan 1965 - Feb 1965 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Withers' book proposal for the Cuban study entitled The Green Island: Life in a Cuban Town, 1947 - 1948 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Select correspondence from Withers to Dr. Espinosa at Stanford University. A book review of Plainville, U.S.A. is included., Aug 1952 - Aug 1961 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Samples of survey and children's folklore collected by Withers, undated (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Carl Withers bequest to the Research Institute for the Study of Man, Nov 1969 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - A memoir by Frank Snowden Hopkins sent to Dr. Rubin. Includes (Xerox) images of Carl L. Withers, Oct 1972 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Obituary published in the American Anthropologist, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence related to Withers' Cuban manuscript, Oct 1972 - Sep 1984 (Box 18, Folder 18)
- Series IX. Oversized Materials, 1947-1984; 1 Linear Feet in one oversize flat box.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains large hand drawn population maps, a print advertisement for Teatro "Eva" Mayjigua, and 14 large format photographs.
  - Hand drawn population maps; print advertisement for Teatro "Eva" Mayjigua, 14 large mounted photographs, Jul 1948, undated (Box 9)
- Series X. Material from Frank Snowden Hopkins, 1937-1976; 1 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains material for a memoir written by Frank Snowden Hopkins, a friend of Carl Withers. Included is correspondence between Hopkins and Withers and Hopkins' and Withers' friends. Also included are writings from Withers and drafts of Hopkins' memoir.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Some items in this series are restricted.
  - Hopkins Correspondence A-C, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Hopkins Correspondence D-H, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Hopkins Correspondence I-M, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Hopkins Correspondence N-R, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Hopkins Correspondence S-Z, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship Applications, RESTRICTED, 1944-1950 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "Plainville, USA" Reviews and Press Clippings, 1944-1955 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "What they say in New England" Reviews and Press Clippings, 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "The Green Island: Folktales from Cuba", undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Misc. Correspondence/Borrowed from Formula, 1958, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Jokes (Anecdotes), 1947, 1949, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Carl's Will, RESTRICTED, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Carl from friends, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Bio data on Carl, RESTRICTED, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Biographical info from Carl's friends, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Grant application, RESTRICTED, 1959-1960 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Addresses re: Carl Withers, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Carl Withers memoir prepared by Hopkins, 1972, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Withers material from A. Jablow/"Chopin in Kansas" by Withers, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Material returned by Esther W. Reno, 1947-1948, 1955, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Carl's letters and writings, 1937, 1946, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Sam Halperin, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Dr. Clark Heath, 1970-1973 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Alta Jablow, 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Memoir pages eliminated in final draft, undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
- Series XI. AV Materials (Material from Jorge Giovanetti)
  - Entrevista a Juan Manuel Picabea (tape 1, part 1) (Box 18, Folder 19, Disc 1, Box Shared University Archives 116, Item 52)
  - Entrevista a Juan Manuel Picabea (tape 1, part 2) (Box 18, Folder 19, Disc 2, Box Shared University Archives 116, Item 53)
  - Entrevista a Juan Manuel Picabea (tape 2) (Box 18, Folder 19, Disc 3, Box Shared University Archives 116, Item 54)
- Series XII. Marcos A. Iglesias' Volumes on Yaguajay, Cuba
  - Cronicas de Yaguajay, Cronica Primera: Yaguajay y las guerras independentistas (1868-1898), 2007 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Yaguajay, Mon Amour: Tus trapiches, tus ingenios, tus centrales, 2005 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Los Caminos de Hierro de Yaguajay, 2003 (Box 12, Folder 19)
- Appendix
  This series contains a binder of copies of Withers materials that were included in an exhibition titled "Retrospect and Prospect: Research Collections and Archives 1955-1985."
  - Withers material copies included in "Retrospect and Prospect: Research Collections and Archives 1955-1985." (Box 10, Folder 10)